{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "A pilot from this nation unwittingly earned a one-hundred thousand dollar prize from the U.S. Air Force when he turned over of a Soviet MiG-15 fighter. Hatchet-wielding soldiers from this nation killed American servicemen in the Joint Security Area, to which the U.S. responded by mobilizing an entire taskforce to cut down a poplar tree in Operation Paul Bunyan. The Demilitarized Zone is shared between a southern neighbor and, for ten points, what East Asian nation dominated for seven decades by the Kim family?",
      "answer": [
        "North Korea",
        "Democratic People's Republic of Korea",
        "or Chosŏn Minjujuŭi Inmin Konghwaguk",
        "or DPRK",
        "DPR Korea",
        "Bukhan"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man piloted a Gonzalo Coelho [[koo-EL-hoh]] voyage to Brazil which encountered its discoverer, Pedro Cabral. This Florentine worked for merchant Gianotto Berardi, who was an early investor in the 1492 Columbus expedition. The cartographer Martin Waldseemüller [[VAHLD-zee-MEW-luh]] was influenced by the Soderini letter to name a landmass for this explorer. For ten points, what Italian navigator, who is credited with coining the term \"New World, is the namesake of two continents in the western hemisphere?",
      "answer": "Amerigo Vespucci"
    },
    {
      "question": "The winning side of this battle issued Order Number 227 before its start, commanding soldiers to take \"not a step back.\" Mamayev [[MAH-mah-yev]] Kurgan and Pavlov’s House were heavily contested locales during this battle. Romanian and German forces in this battle were encircled by Operation Uranus, led by Georgy Zhukov. For ten points, name this battle where Friedrich Paulus’s Sixth Army failed to take a city on the Volga named for the leader of the Soviet Union.",
      "answer": "Battle of Stalingrad"
    },
    {
      "question": "Polish forces deployed an armored variant of this product known as the \"FT-B\" in an effort to repel a Russian invasion during the 1920 Polish-Soviet War. The creator of this product joked that you can have it \"any color, so long as it is black\" during a board meeting. This was the most sold automobile of the early 20th century. The \"Tin Lizzie\" was a nickname for, for ten points, which first mass-produced car created by the Ford Motor Company?",
      "answer": "Ford Model T"
    },
    {
      "question": "Dirt brought from this state was used to bury the Marquis [[mahr-KEE]] de Lafayette in Paris. The storming of this state's Springfield Armory occurred during Shays' Rebellion, an uprising of disenchanted Revolutionary War veterans. Israel Putnam legendarily said \"Don't fire 'til you see the whites of their eyes\" at a 1775 engagement with the Redcoats in this state. The Battle of Bunker Hill occurred in, for ten points, what New England state?",
      "answer": "Massachusetts"
    },
    {
      "question": "This figure held 1960s jazz concerts in his backyard, including acts like Dave Brubeck and Dizzy Gillespie, to raise funds for the Southern Christian Leadership Conference. This founder of the Black-owned Freedom National Bank was defended by teammate Pee-Wee Reese by saying \"You can hate a man for many reasons. Color is not one of them.\" The first Black man to break the color barrier in Major League Baseball was, for ten points, which Brooklyn Dodgers baseball player?",
      "answer": "Jackie Robinson or Jack Roosevelt Robinson"
    },
    {
      "question": "The outbreak of the Austro-Turkish war forced this composer to move from Vienna to Alsegrund. This man employed his own sister-in-law Josefa Weber [[yoh-SEH-fah VEH- buh]] to perform the role of Queen of the Night in one opera. The marriage of the Emperor's niece led to the city of Prague commissioning this composer's Don Giovanni. The Marriage of Figaro and The Magic Flute were written by, for ten points, which German-language composer of the 18th century?",
      "answer": [
        "Wolfgang Amadeus Mozart",
        "Johannes Chrysostomus Wolfgangus Theophilus Mozart"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Roy Choi created a popular variety of these objects in southern California known as Kogi. A variety of these objects that often frequent construction sites are known as “roach coaches.” In accordance with its roots, a popular New England variety of these objects called Roxy’s sells a product known as the Green Muenster. These objects may have grown out of the chuck wagon. In the 1970s, Raul Martinez pioneered the use of these objects to sell tacos. For ten points, name these vehicles where one can grab a meal.",
      "answer": "Food Trucks"
    },
    {
      "question": "Frederick Jackson Turner's Frontier Thesis claims \"American Democracy\" was not established on this object or the Susan Constant. The springing of a leak by the accompanying Speedwell led to William Bradford deciding to solely use this ship for a western voyage. A rudimentary government for Plymouth known as its namesake \"Compact\" was signed on this vessel. For ten points, name this ship that transported the Pilgrims to the New World.",
      "answer": "Mayflower 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 3"
    },
    {
      "question": "William Hogarth depicted a young merchant wasting his money in this city and eventually being placed in its Fleet Prison in A Rake's Progress. Waterloo Bridge and Charing Cross Bridge are included in Claude Monet's scenes from this city, which include a series on the Houses of Parliament. Canaletto painted The Thames and the City depicting, for ten points, which English capital city that contains the Tate Modern?",
      "answer": "London 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 3"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In this city's amphitheater, Pink Floyd member David Gilmour gave the first public concert here in over 1,900 years. This site includes the ancient House of the Surgeon, as well as several artworks depicting Greek mythology in the House of the Tragic Poet. The Alexander Mosaic is found in this site's House of the Faun, which occupies an entire insula. For ten points, name this city which, along with Herculaneum, was destroyed by the 79 C.E. eruption of Mount Vesuvius.",
        "answer": "Pompeii or Pumpeje"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Pompeii is close to this modern Italian city, which was conquered by the Romans during the Samnite Wars. It was later the longest-serving capital of the Kingdom of the Two Sicilies.",
        "answer": [
          "Naples or Napoli",
          "or Napule",
          "Neapolis"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One leader of this nation launched the Infitah [[in-fee-TAH]] policy, which \"opened the door\" to western investment. During a parade celebrating Operation Badr [[BAD-er]] in this nation, that leader was assassinated by members of the Islamic Jihad. Protests in this country's Tahrir Square in 2011 led to the ousting of long-time president Hosni Mubarak. Since 2014, Abdel Fattah el-Sisi has served as president of, for ten points, what Arab nation governed from Cairo?",
        "answer": "Egypt"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "During Operation Badr, the Egyptian Army captured part of the Sinai [[\"SIGH\"-nye]] Peninsula from this Middle Eastern neighbor, led at the time by Golda Meir [[GOHL-duh may-EER]].",
        "answer": [
          "Israel or Yisra'el",
          "State of Israel",
          "or Medinat Yisra'el"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This ruler approached his cousin of the same name to force him to become dictator, though that Grand Duke responded by pointing a pistol at his own head and threatening to fire. That episode occurred during the Revolution of 1905, in which this ruler's forces fired on demonstrators during \"Bloody Sunday\" at the Winter Palace. The Russo-Japanese War was lost by, for ten points, which Tsar who was later killed by the Bolsheviks?",
        "answer": [
          "Nicholas II",
          "Nikolai II"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Nicholas II's reforms during the Revolution of 1905 created this parliamentary body of Russia, the name of which is still carried by the lower house of Russian parliament.",
        "answer": [
          "State Duma or Imperial Duma",
          "Imperial State Duma",
          "Gosudarstvennaya Duma 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 3"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The Postmaster General in the Harding Cabinet, Will H. Hays, names a regulatory \"Code\" for this industry, which banned depictions of \"homosexuality\" and \"unnecessary violence.\" The revival of the Second Ku Klux Klan in Stone Mountain, Georgia was sparked by a production in this industry called Birth of a Nation. For ten points, name this industry whose studios were forbidden from owning theaters in the court case United States v. Paramount Pictures.",
        "answer": [
          "Film",
          "the Movie Industry",
          "Motion Pictures"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "One of Stanley Kubrick's early films revolves around this ancient Roman gladiator- turned leader of a slave rebellion. In an often-parodied climactic scene, this man's allies refuse to identify him, instead claiming \"I'm [this man]!\"",
        "answer": [
          "Spartacus",
          "\"I'm Spartacus!\"",
          "Spártakos"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In one poem, William Wordsworth referred to this site as an \"Inmate of lonesome Nature's endless year.\" After stabbing Alec, Tess of the D'urbervilles finally surrenders to police at this monument, which lies in Wiltshire. The works of William Stukeley led to the popular connection between this monument and the order of druids. For ten points, name this prehistoric monument on the Salisbury Plain that is often featured in British literature.",
        "answer": "Stonehenge"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In a radio serial, this fictional detective investigates the death of a Presbyterian minister at Stonehenge. This character's aide was wounded while fighting in Afghanistan during the Great Game era.",
        "answer": "Sherlock Holmes"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This was the most popular service restricted by India following a conflict near Ladakh. Along with WeChat, this service was the subject of an executive order giving it forty-five days to divest its U.S. holdings or be purchased by an American company. In 2018, this service's parent company, ByteDance, merged it with Musical.ly, a similar Chinese social media service. For ten points, name this popular video-sharing social networking service, known in China as Douyin.",
        "answer": [
          "TikTok",
          "Douyin before mentioned"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "TikTok successfully filled the void created when this Twitter-owned service was discontinued. This service allowed users to share six-second long videos on a loop.",
        "answer": "Vine 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 3"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man was unknowingly given small dosages of methamphetamines by Max Jacobson, who was nicknamed \"Dr. Feelgood.\" This politician defeated incumbent Henry Cabot Lodge Jr. in a 1952 Senate race. This president negotiated with Nikita Khrushchev [[KROO-shev]] during the Cuban Missile Crisis and was in office during the botched Bay of Pigs invasion. The youngest person ever elected president was, for ten points, which Massachusetts politician?",
        "answer": [
          "John F. Kennedy both underlined portions required",
          "JFK"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The name of this mythical castle of Arthurian legend was used to evoke the general positive feelings of the American public toward the Kennedy family during their time in the White House.",
        "answer": [
          "Camelot",
          "Camelot era"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A thinker from this country criticized the Gotha [[GOH-tah]] Programme of its Social Democratic Party in one pamphlet. Another thinker from this country argued that a “Protestant work ethic” enabled the development of modern capitalism and suggested that the state held a monopoly on the legitimate use of violence. Two writers originally from this country wrote the Communist Manifesto. For ten points, name this homeland of Friedrich Engels, Max Weber [[VEH-buh]], and Karl Marx.",
        "answer": [
          "Germany or Deutschland",
          "German Reich",
          "or Deutsches Reich",
          "the Kingdom of Prussia",
          "Königreich Preußen"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This German philosopher, who stated \"God is dead,\" suggested that human history changed when people went from thinking of \"good and bad\" to \"good and evil.\"",
        "answer": "Friedrich Nietzsche ] or Friedrich Wilhelm Nietzsche"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Regarding the administration of Bill Clinton, name the...",
      "prompt": "Name the regarding the administration of bill clinton, name the......",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Prosperous decade during which the majority of Clinton's presidency occurred.",
          "answer": "1990s"
        },
        {
          "question": "White House intern subjected to a sex scandal along with the sitting President.",
          "answer": "Monica Lewinsky or Monica Samille Lewinsky"
        },
        {
          "question": "Supreme Court Justice, nicknamed RBG, who was nominated to be the second woman to serve on the court.",
          "answer": "Ruth Bader Ginsburg"
        },
        {
          "question": "Agreement signed by the Clinton administration, which was succeeded by Donald Trump’s USMCA.",
          "answer": [
            "NAFTA",
            "North American Free Trade Agreement"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Corrupt real estate venture which was investigated during the Clinton years.",
          "answer": [
            "Whitewater Development Corporation",
            "Whitewater Scandal/Controversy"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Female Attorney General who ordered the assault on the Waco compound.",
          "answer": "Janet Reno or Janet Wood Reno"
        },
        {
          "question": "Agreement named for an Ohio city which ended the Bosnian War.",
          "answer": "Dayton Accords"
        },
        {
          "question": "Law which was repealed, requiring commercial banks and investment banks to be separate.",
          "answer": "Glass-Steagall Act 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 3"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "The Congress of Vienna",
      "prompt": "Name the the congress of vienna...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "French Emperor whose deposition and exile led to the convening of the Congress of Vienna.",
          "answer": [
            "Napoleon Bonaparte",
            "either underlined portion"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Nation, known as the Helvetic Republic under Napoleonic rule, whose 22 cantons had their perpetual neutrality guaranteed.",
          "answer": [
            "Switzerland",
            "Swiss Confederation"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Kingdom tied to the Russian throne which was formerly known as the Duchy of Warsaw.",
          "answer": [
            "Kingdom of Poland or Królestwo Polskie",
            "Congress Poland"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Austrian statesman who organized the Congress of Vienna.",
          "answer": "Klemens von Metternich"
        },
        {
          "question": "Tsar of Russia who seized the Grand Duchy of Finland for himself at the congress.",
          "answer": "Alexander I"
        },
        {
          "question": "Diplomat and perpetual turncoat who represented France at the Congress.",
          "answer": "Charles-Maurice de Talleyrand"
        },
        {
          "question": "French military commander who was allowed to retain his role as regent of Sweden, eventually becoming its king.",
          "answer": [
            "Jean-Baptiste Bernadotte",
            "Charles XIV [[the fourteenth John"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Island kingdom that unified with Savoy and regained its mainland territories in the Congress.",
          "answer": "Kingdom of Sardinia 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 3 African Decolonization"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Regarding the end of colonialism in Africa, name the...",
      "prompt": "Name the regarding the end of colonialism in africa, name the......",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "American territory-turned-independent nation whose capital was named for the fifth U.S. president.",
          "answer": "Republic of Liberia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Former member of French West Africa which is named for a medieval African empire led by mansas.",
          "answer": [
            "Republic of Mali or République du Mali",
            "or Mali ka Fasojamana",
            "or Renndaandi Maali"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Nation formed in 1957 from the Gold Coast and Ashanti colonies, led by Kwame Nkrumah [[KWAH-meh en-KROO-muh]]",
          "answer": "Republic of Ghana"
        },
        {
          "question": "North African country whose war for independence led to the collapse of the French Fourth Republic.",
          "answer": "People's Democratic Republic of Algeria"
        },
        {
          "question": "British colony which experienced the Mau Mau Uprising before becoming independent in 1963.",
          "answer": "Republic of Kenya or Jamhuri ya Kenya"
        },
        {
          "question": "Portuguese-speaking country whose civil war included the participation of Cuban troops.",
          "answer": "Republic of Angola or República de Angola"
        },
        {
          "question": "Former German colony which became independent from South Africa in 1990.",
          "answer": "Republic of Namibia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Secessionist Igbo state that broke away from Nigeria during their post- independence civil war.",
          "answer": "Republic of Biafra 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 3"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Under this prime minister, a scandal over the merger of Westland Helicopters led to the resignation of Defense Secretary Michael Heseltine. “Flying (20 pts)",
        "pickets” were used by National Union of Mineworkers during a strike under this prime minister. This leader’s victory in the Falklands War allowed a landslide Conservative victory in the 1983 (10 pts)",
        "general election. For ten points, name this “Iron Lady,” the prime minister of the United Kingdom during the 1980s."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Margaret Thatcher or Margaret Hilda Thatcher",
        "Baroness Thatcher"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The Antikythera [[AN-tih-kih-THEER-uh]] mechanism is believed to be the oldest example of an analogue type of this device. The Difference Engine was (20 pts)",
        "a prototype of one of these devices built by Charles Babbage. German engineer Konrad Zuse [[ZOO-suh]] developed the Z3, the first programmable digital example of these devices, during World War (10 pts)",
        "Two. For ten points, name these devices that rapidly carry out mathematical operations, the \"science\" for which was pioneered by Alan Turing."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Computers",
        "Analogue Computers",
        "or Electromechanical Computer",
        "or Computer Science"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This party accepted opponent William Pitt Kellogg's election as governor of Louisiana in exchange for house seats in the Wheeler Compromise. This party's historical factions included the white supremacist (20 pts)",
        "Redeemers, the pro-big business Bourbons, and the Populists of William Jennings Bryan. This party controlled the \"Solid South,\" though it lost control of Southern states during the Reagan era. Represented by a (10 pts)",
        "donkey, for ten points, what U.S. political party opposes the Republicans?"
      ],
      "answer": "Democratic Party or Democrats"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This person's first purported miracle occurred when a locket containing their image supposedly rid Monica Besra of a malignant tumor. This figure faced controversy for her tacit support of her homeland's Hoxha [[HOH-shuh]] regime (20 pts)",
        "and Indira Gandhi's suspension of civil liberties during \"The Emergency.\" This woman of Albanian descent founded the Missionaries of Charity and served the slums of (10 pts)",
        "Kolkata. For ten points, name this Nobel Peace Prize winner and canonized nun of the 20th century."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Mother Teresa",
        "Mary Teresa Bojaxhiu",
        "Saint Teresa of Calcutta 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 3"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "This monument’s astylar design was developed by the Neoclassical sculptor Jean Chalgrin [[SHAHL-grin]]. The base of this monument contains four sculptural groups, including one by Antoine (*) Etex said to commemorate the Peace of 1815 and one by François [[frahn-SWAH]] Rude called Departure of the Volunteers of 1792. The Tomb of the Unknown Soldier beneath this monument was commissioned after the Battle of (*) Austerlitz. For ten points, name this monument found at the western end of the Champs-Élysées [[SHAHMPS eh-lee-SAY]] in Paris."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Arc de Triomphe de l'Étoile",
        "Triumphal Arch of the Star"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "This man urged the common British person to abandon so-called \"dying metaphors\" in his essay \"Politics and the English Language.\" This writer's participation in the POUM (*) party's militia during the Spanish Civil War inspired his autobiographical Homage to Catalonia. This man's time as police sub-commandant in British Burma inspired his short story \"Shooting an Elephant.\" The rise of totalitarianism (*) inspired, for ten points, which British writer's 1984 and Animal Farm?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "George Orwell",
        "Eric Arthur Blair"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "Dominique de Gourgues [[GOORZH]] temporarily reestablished French hegemony in the north of this state by seizing Fort Caroline. A 1521 voyage to this modern state ended with its leader dying following a skirmish with the Calusa people. (*) The oldest continuously inhabited settlement in the U.S. is in this state. The conquistador Juan Ponce de Leon searched for the \"Fountain of (*) Youth\" in, for ten points, which Southern U.S. state that contains St. Augustine?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Florida",
        "La Florida",
        "or Floride"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Gepid king Ardaric quickly collapsed an empire named for these people after gathering its former subject tribes and defeating them at the Battle of Nedao [[NEH- dow]]. Allied with the Visigothic king Theoderic, (20 pts)",
        "the Roman general Flavius Aetius [[AY-shus]] stopped these people's advance into Western Europe at the Battle of the Catalaunian Plains. Much of 5th century (10 pts)",
        "Europe was ravaged by, for ten points, what nomadic people led by Attila?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Huns",
        "Hunnic people",
        "or Hunnish 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 3"
      ]
    }
  ]
}